<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<akomaNtoso xmlns="http://docs.oasis-open.org/legaldocml/ns/akn/3.0/WD17">
  <bill name="bill">
    <meta>
      <identification source="">
        <FRBRWork>
          <FRBRthis value="/ie/oireachtas/bill/2016/24"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/ie/oireachtas/bill/2016/24"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2016-05-16" name="introduced"/>
          <FRBRauthor href=""/>
          <FRBRcountry value="IE"/>
          <FRBRnumber value="24"/>
        </FRBRWork>
        <FRBRExpression>
          <FRBRthis value="/ie/oireachtas/bill/2016/24/initiated/en"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/ie/oireachtas/bill/2016/24/initiated/en"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2016-05-16" name="published"/>
          <FRBRauthor href=""/>
          <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
        </FRBRExpression>
        <FRBRManifestation>
          <FRBRthis value="/ie/oireachtas/bill/2016/24/initiated/en/xml"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/ie/oireachtas/bill/2016/24/initiated/en/xml"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2016-10-23" name="transformed"/>
          <FRBRauthor href=""/>
          <FRBRformat value="application/akn+xml"/>
        </FRBRManifestation>
      </identification>
    </meta>
    <coverPage>
      <p>
        <img src=""/>
      </p>
      <block name="horizontal-rule"/>
      <p class="short-title irish">
        <shortTitle xml:lang="ga">Bille an Bhainc Ceannais (Morgáistí Ráta Athraithigh), 2016</shortTitle>
      </p>
      <p class="short-title english">
        <shortTitle xml:lang="en">Central Bank (Variable Rate Mortgages) Bill 2016</shortTitle>
      </p>
      <block name="horizontal-rule"/>
      <p style="as-initiated">Mar a tionscnaíodh</p>
      <p style="as-initiated">As initiated</p>
      <block name="horizontal-rule"/>
      <p>
        <img src=""/>
      </p>
      <block name="horizontal-rule"/>
      <p class="short-title irish">
        <shortTitle xml:lang="ga">BILLE AN BHAINC CEANNAIS (MORGÁISTÍ RÁTA ATHRAITHIGH), 2016</shortTitle>
      </p>
      <p class="short-title english">
        <shortTitle xml:lang="en">Central Bank (Variable Rate Mortgages) Bill 2016</shortTitle>
      </p>
      <block name="horizontal-rule"/>
      <p class="statusirish">Mar a tionscnaíodh</p>
      <p class="statusenglish">As initiated</p>
      <block name="horizontal-rule"/>
      <toc>
        <tocItem class="heading" href="" level="0">CONTENTS</tocItem>
        <tocItem class="heading" href="" level="0">Section</tocItem>
        <tocItem class="section" href="#toc_book_1" level="1">
          <inline name="tocNum">1.</inline>
          <inline name="tocHeading">Definitions</inline>
        </tocItem>
        <tocItem class="section" href="#toc_book_2" level="1">
          <inline name="tocNum">2.</inline>
          <inline name="tocHeading">Section 2 Assessments</inline>
        </tocItem>
        <tocItem class="section" href="#toc_book_3" level="1">
          <inline name="tocNum">3.</inline>
          <inline name="tocHeading">Factors to which Central Bank shall have regard</inline>
        </tocItem>
        <tocItem class="section" href="#toc_book_4" level="1">
          <inline name="tocNum">4.</inline>
          <inline name="tocHeading">Formation of conclusion</inline>
        </tocItem>
        <tocItem class="section" href="#toc_book_5" level="1">
          <inline name="tocNum">5.</inline>
          <inline name="tocHeading">Power to issue direction to lender</inline>
        </tocItem>
        <tocItem class="section" href="#toc_book_6" level="1">
          <inline name="tocNum">6.</inline>
          <inline name="tocHeading">Enforcement Orders</inline>
        </tocItem>
        <tocItem class="section" href="#toc_book_7" level="1">
          <inline name="tocNum">7.</inline>
          <inline name="tocHeading">Prohibition on discrimination against existing customers</inline>
        </tocItem>
        <tocItem class="section" href="#toc_book_8" level="1">
          <inline name="tocNum">8.</inline>
          <inline name="tocHeading">Rectification Orders and Compensation Orders</inline>
        </tocItem>
        <tocItem class="section" href="#toc_book_9" level="1">
          <inline name="tocNum">9.</inline>
          <inline name="tocHeading">Defrayal of legal costs or stamp duty not to constitute discrimination</inline>
        </tocItem>
        <tocItem class="section" href="#toc_book_10" level="1">
          <inline name="tocNum">10.</inline>
          <inline name="tocHeading">Publication of Section 2 Assessments</inline>
        </tocItem>
        <tocItem class="section" href="#toc_book_11" level="1">
          <inline name="tocNum">11.</inline>
          <inline name="tocHeading">No appeal from decision of Central Bank</inline>
        </tocItem>
        <tocItem class="section" href="#toc_book_12" level="1">
          <inline name="tocNum">12.</inline>
          <inline name="tocHeading">Short title and commencement</inline>
        </tocItem>
      </toc>
      <tblock class="acts-referred-to">
        <heading>Act Referred to</heading>
        <p class="act-referred-to">Central Bank Act 1942 (No. 22)</p>
      </tblock>
    </coverPage>
    <preface>
      <p>
        <img src=""/>
      </p>
      <block name="horizontal-rule"/>
      <p class="short-title irish">
        <shortTitle xml:lang="ga">BILLE AN BHAINC CEANNAIS (MORGÁISTÍ RÁTA ATHRAITHIGH), 2016</shortTitle>
      </p>
      <p class="short-title english">
        <shortTitle xml:lang="en">Central Bank (Variable Rate Mortgages) Bill 2016</shortTitle>
      </p>
      <block name="horizontal-rule"/>
      <p>
        <docType>Bill</docType>
      </p>
      <p class="entitled">entitled</p>
      <longTitle>
        <p>An Act to provide for measures to address market failures in the market for principal <eol/>dwelling house mortgage loans, and to provide for related matters.</p>
      </longTitle>
    </preface>
    <preamble>
      <formula name="enacted">
        <p>Be it enacted by the Oireachtas as follows:</p>
      </formula>
    </preamble>
    <body>
      <section wId="sec_1">
        <heading>Definitions</heading>
        <num>1.</num>
        <intro>
          <p>In this Act⁠—</p>
        </intro>
        <subsection wId="sec_1__subsec_1">
          <content>
            <p>“Central Bank” means the Central Bank of Ireland;</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection wId="sec_1__subsec_2">
          <content>
            <p>“Compensation Order” shall have the meaning ascribed to it by <i>section</i> <i>8</i> <i>(3)</i>;</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection wId="sec_1__subsec_3">
          <content>
            <p>“Enforcement Order” shall be interpreted with regard to <i>section</i> <i>6</i>;</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection wId="sec_1__subsec_4">
          <content>
            <p>“lender” shall include any regulated financial service provider within the meaning of the <eol/>Central Bank Act 1942 or any company, partnership, business or other entity engaged in <eol/>the provision, management or administration of principal dwelling house mortgage loans;</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection wId="sec_1__subsec_5">
          <content>
            <p>“principal dwelling house mortgage loan” shall mean a loan for the primary purpose of <eol/>purchasing a principal dwelling home for the borrower (and if relevant the family of the <eol/>borrower) on an owner-occupier business;</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection wId="sec_1__subsec_6">
          <content>
            <p>“Rectification Order” shall have the meaning ascribed to it by <i>section</i> <i>8</i> <i>(1)</i>;</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection wId="sec_1__subsec_7">
          <content>
            <p>“<i>Section </i> <i>2</i> Assessment” shall mean an assessment carried out pursuant to <i>section</i> <i>2</i>;</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection wId="sec_1__subsec_8">
          <intro>
            <p>“variable interest rate” shall⁠—</p>
          </intro>
          <paragraph wId="sec_1__subsec_8__para_a">
            <num>(a)</num>
            <content>
              <p>include any interest rate which is transient or otherwise not fixed and which is <eol/>not set or calculated by reference to an interest rate set or otherwise determined <eol/>by the European Central Bank,</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
          <paragraph wId="sec_1__subsec_8__para_b">
            <num>(b)</num>
            <content>
              <p>in relation to a lender, include a reference to different variable interest rates being <eol/>charged by a lender in respect of different principal dwelling house mortgage <eol/>loans or categories of principal dwelling house mortgage loans.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section wId="sec_2">
        <heading>Section 2 Assessments</heading>
        <num>2.</num>
        <content>
          <p>The Central Bank shall carry out assessments on the state of competition in the market <eol/>for principal dwelling house mortgage loans on at least a quarterly basis.</p>
        </content>
      </section>
      <section wId="sec_3">
        <heading>Factors to which Central Bank shall have regard</heading>
        <num>3.</num>
        <intro>
          <p>In carrying out a <i>S</i><i>ection</i> <i>2</i> Assessment, the Central Bank shall have regard to the <eol/>following factors:</p>
        </intro>
        <paragraph wId="sec_3__para_a">
          <num>(a)</num>
          <content>
            <p>the variable interest rates being charged by lenders;</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
        <paragraph wId="sec_3__para_b">
          <num>(b)</num>
          <content>
            <p>the ease with which borrowers can switch their principal dwelling house <eol/>mortgage loans between lenders or between products offered by the same lender;</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
        <paragraph wId="sec_3__para_c">
          <num>(c)</num>
          <content>
            <p>the extent to which borrowers are switching their principal dwelling house <eol/>mortgage loans between lenders or between products offered by the same lender;</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
        <paragraph wId="sec_3__para_d">
          <num>(d)</num>
          <content>
            <p>the relationship and proportionality between the variable interest rates being <eol/>charged by each lender and the cost of funds of that lender;</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
        <paragraph wId="sec_3__para_e">
          <num>(e)</num>
          <content>
            <p>the trend in variable interest rates being charged in the principal dwelling house <eol/>mortgage loan market over time;</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
        <paragraph wId="sec_3__para_f">
          <num>(f)</num>
          <content>
            <p>lenders’ cost of funds and the trend in lenders’ cost of funds over time;</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
        <paragraph wId="sec_3__para_g">
          <num>(g)</num>
          <content>
            <p>lenders’ weighted average cost of capital and the trend in lenders’ weighted <eol/>average costs of capital over time;</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
        <paragraph wId="sec_3__para_h">
          <num>(h)</num>
          <content>
            <p>the risk profiles of individual lenders in respect of variable interest rate principal <eol/>dwelling house mortgage loans;</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
        <paragraph wId="sec_3__para_i">
          <num>(i)</num>
          <content>
            <p>lenders’ reasonable profit expectations in the prevailing market conditions;</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
        <paragraph wId="sec_3__para_j">
          <num>(j)</num>
          <content>
            <p>the proportion of the principal dwelling house mortgage loan market accounted <eol/>for by each lender; and</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
        <paragraph wId="sec_3__para_k">
          <num>(k)</num>
          <content>
            <p>such other matters as the Governor of the Central Bank may certify as being of <eol/>relevance.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section wId="sec_4">
        <heading>Formation of conclusion</heading>
        <num>4.</num>
        <subsection wId="sec_4__subsec_1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Upon completion of a <i>Section</i> <i>2</i> Assessment, the Central Bank shall form a conclusion <eol/>as to whether the state of competition in the market for principal dwelling house <eol/>mortgage loans is such that a market failure exists.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection wId="sec_4__subsec_2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>For the purposes of this Act, “market failure” shall mean a situation in which market <eol/>conditions are such that a lender is, or lenders are, charging a variable interest rate or <eol/>variable interest rates for principal dwelling house mortgage loans which are higher <eol/>than the Central Bank considers can be reasonably and objectively justified by <eol/>reference to the factors set out in <i>section</i> <i>3</i>.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section wId="sec_5">
        <heading>Power to issue direction to lender</heading>
        <num>5.</num>
        <intro>
          <p>Where the Central Bank forms a conclusion pursuant to <i>section</i> <i>4</i> that a market failure <eol/>exists, the Central Bank may issue a direction to a specific lender or lenders (or lenders <eol/>in general) not to charge a variable interest rate or variable interest rates in respect of <eol/>principal dwelling house mortgage loans generally, or specific principal dwelling house <eol/>mortgage loans or categories of principal dwelling house mortgage loans, which <eol/>exceeds⁠—</p>
        </intro>
        <paragraph wId="sec_5__para_a">
          <num>(a)</num>
          <content>
            <p>a rate or rates specified by the Central Bank,</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
        <paragraph wId="sec_5__para_b">
          <num>(b)</num>
          <content>
            <p>a margin or margins specified by the Central Bank above that lender’s cost of <eol/>funds (as determined by the Central Bank),</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
        <paragraph wId="sec_5__para_c">
          <num>(c)</num>
          <content>
            <p>a margin or margins specified by the Central Bank above a rate set by the <eol/>European Central Bank nominated by the Central Bank, and/or</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
        <paragraph wId="sec_5__para_d">
          <num>(d)</num>
          <content>
            <p>a proportion, being not more than one-third, specified by the Central Bank above <eol/>the average variable interest rate charged in the market for comparable principal <eol/>dwelling house mortgage loans as determined by the Central Bank.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section wId="sec_6">
        <heading>Enforcement Orders</heading>
        <num>6.</num>
        <subsection wId="sec_6__subsec_1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>A direction pursuant to <i>section</i> <i>5</i> shall state the duration for which the direction shall <eol/>remain in force, which may be an indefinite period, but such a direction may <eol/>subsequently be extended, varied or brought to an end by the Central Bank at any <eol/>time.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection wId="sec_6__subsec_2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>A lender shall comply with a direction pursuant to <i>section</i> <i>5</i> (or any variation of such <eol/>a direction) within 56 days from the date of the direction (or variation as the case may <eol/>be) and shall thereafter continue to comply with the direction until such time, if any, <eol/>that it is varied or brought to an end by the Central Bank.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection wId="sec_6__subsec_3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Where the Central Bank believes that a lender is in breach of <i>subsection</i> <i>(2)</i>, it may <eol/>apply to the High Court on notice to the lender in question for an Enforcement Order <eol/>requiring the lender in question to comply with the direction in question.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection wId="sec_6__subsec_4">
          <num>(4)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Upon hearing an application pursuant to <i>subsection</i> <i>(3)</i>, the High Court shall grant an <eol/>Enforcement Order if it determines that the lender in question is in breach of the <eol/>relevant direction.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection wId="sec_6__subsec_5">
          <num>(5)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Where the High Court makes an Enforcement Order in accordance with this section, it <eol/>shall impose a fine on the lender in question in the sum of twice the amount that the <eol/>court determines the lender derived in profits in breach of the relevant direction, <eol/>unless the court determines that it would be unjust to impose such a fine, in which <eol/>case it may impose a lesser fine or dispense with the requirement to impose a fine.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section wId="sec_7">
        <heading>Prohibition on discrimination against existing customers</heading>
        <num>7.</num>
        <content>
          <p>In setting a variable interest rate for a group, class or category of principal dwelling <eol/>house mortgage loans, a lender may not discriminate between existing borrowers and <eol/>new borrowers.</p>
        </content>
      </section>
      <section wId="sec_8">
        <heading>Rectification Orders and Compensation Orders</heading>
        <num>8.</num>
        <subsection wId="sec_8__subsec_1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Where the Central Bank believes that a lender is in breach of its obligations pursuant <eol/>to <i>section</i> <i>7</i>, the Central Bank may apply to the High Court on notice to the lender in <eol/>question for a Rectification Order requiring the lender in question to cease the <eol/>relevant discriminatory practice prohibited by <i>section</i> <i>7</i>.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection wId="sec_8__subsec_2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Upon hearing an application pursuant to <i>subsection</i> <i>(1)</i>, the High Court shall grant a <eol/>Rectification Order in such terms as the court deems appropriate if it determines that <eol/>the lender in question has acted in breach of <i>section</i> <i>7</i>.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection wId="sec_8__subsec_3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Where the High Court makes a Rectification Order in accordance with this section, it <eop/>shall make a Compensation Order in such terms as the court considers appropriate <eol/>requiring the lender to compensate any borrower or former borrower (or class of <eol/>borrowers or former borrowers) of the lender affected by the discriminatory practice <eol/>in question unless the court believes it would be unjust to do so.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection wId="sec_8__subsec_4">
          <num>(4)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Where the High Court makes a Rectification Order in accordance with this section, it <eol/>shall impose a fine on the lender in question in the sum of twice the amount that the <eol/>court determines the lender derived in profits on foot of the discriminatory practice in <eol/>question, unless the court determines that it would be unjust to impose such a fine, in <eol/>which case it may impose a lesser fine or dispense with the requirement to impose a <eol/>fine.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section wId="sec_9">
        <heading>Defrayal of legal costs or stamp duty not to constitute discrimination</heading>
        <num>9.</num>
        <intro>
          <p>A lender shall not be regarded as discriminating between existing borrowers and new <eol/>borrowers for the purposes of <i>section</i> <i>7</i> as a consequence of providing new borrowers <eol/>with a once-off payment or discount for the purpose of defraying on a <i>bona fide</i> and <eol/>vouched basis⁠—</p>
        </intro>
        <paragraph wId="sec_9__para_a">
          <num>(a)</num>
          <content>
            <p>the borrowers’ legal costs in taking out the loans in question or switching <eol/>between loan products, and/or</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
        <paragraph wId="sec_9__para_b">
          <num>(b)</num>
          <content>
            <p>the borrowers’ liability for stamp duty in the purchase of the principal dwelling <eol/>house in question.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section wId="sec_10">
        <heading>Publication of Section 2 Assessments</heading>
        <num>10.</num>
        <content>
          <p>The Central Bank shall publish each <i>Section</i> <i>2</i> Assessment publicly in such a manner as it <eol/>considers appropriate.</p>
        </content>
      </section>
      <section wId="sec_11">
        <heading>No appeal from decision of Central Bank</heading>
        <num>11.</num>
        <content>
          <p>Notwithstanding the provisions of the Central Bank Act 1942 or any other enactment, no <eol/>appeal shall lie to the Irish Financial Services Appeals Tribunal or the High Court in <eol/>respect of a <i>Section</i> <i>2</i> Assessment, a direction pursuant to <i>section</i> <i>5</i> or a decision by the <eol/>Central Bank to seek an Enforcement Order or a Rectification Order.</p>
        </content>
      </section>
      <section wId="sec_12">
        <heading>Short title and commencement</heading>
        <num>12.</num>
        <subsection wId="sec_12__subsec_1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>This Act shall be cited as the Central Bank (Variable Rate Mortgages) Act 2016.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection wId="sec_12__subsec_2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>This Act shall come into effect immediately.</p>
            <p/>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
    </body>
  </bill>
</akomaNtoso>
